um we're in the middle of the Perfection
of giving and the Perfection of giving
is important for Diamond way especially
for your diamond wave
vows uh in the diamond wave vows you're
supposed to do four kinds of
giving and that's related to one of the
five Buddha families named
ratnakara which is
south and uh generally connected to a
yellow
color and there are four kinds of giving
there and uh they're they're supposed to
be put in here just to put a seed in
your mind okay later when you take your
diamond wave
vows uh you make a commitment to these
four kinds of giving so you might as
well get ready
anyway uh first
one is easy material things you know
giving away money give away coffee stuff
like
that
[Music]
okay the second kind of giving that you
commit
to is called
protection and the names are secret the
names of the four kinds of giving are
hidden uh so in that case protection
means
equinity and it doesn't mean protecting
people it means treating people equally
okay
uh I think in my life it's not so much
uh people of different races or people
of different
genders or people of different
countries uh I think I have
trouble treating people of different
political parties the
same just but I mean this is the kind of
equinity okay like treat everyone the
same and
uh it I mean I think we all have
different
prejudices and it's important to know
that you have prejudices uh but I think
the one to watch out for uh in in my
case or maybe many Dharma people is uh
prejudice against people with different
viewpoints okay so uh if you're going to
follow Diamond way if you're going to
keep the vows of r
ARA uh part of that is to be accepting
of people with different view points
okay uh equinity Third Kind of giving
for ratnakara is Dharma giving
Dharma and again it can just be in a
conversation on a bus or something okay
like
that and then in in the vows of
ratnakara you're supposed to give love
The Fourth Kind of giving is
love
uh but it covers uh not getting
angry and it covers uh speaking sweetly
with truth speaking to people with truth
okay those are all kinds of lovees so
those are the different kinds of giving
when you talk about perfection of
giving there's a different level when
you reach Diamond way okay and it's
mostly to do with Bo
ratnakar with the southern budha okay
so you'll learn more about it later I'm
just planting a seed okay four kinds of
giving and they are not what they sound
like okay
um let's go back to the
text means help people in the prisons
and uh we had a really
good uh prison project here and we used
to go to the prisons a lot and uh
there's a prison north of
tuon uh and uh we used to have a center
in Phoenix so it was easy to go to the
prison now to go to the prison from
where we live it's like it's a eight
hour
trip and we kind of don't do it as much
as we used to uh but we still have
teachers teaching in the prison he makes
a special point
that people in the prison are are
especially suffering people who who are
staying in prison yeah and America has
this Pro problem worse than other
countries we have a very large I think
we have the largest prison population in
the world and uh so Arizona is one of
the places where they build the prisons
because the land is cheap we have
prisons and semiconductor
plants because the land is cheap and the
labor cheap so
um uh he's saying it's a special Good
Karma to get involved with prisons and
and we did for many years I think we
kind of slacked off the people the
person in charge got cancer and passed
away Jeff
Eddie and uh so we haven't done much but
it's a special Good Karma and uh my my
personal experience in the prisons was
uh
people are very very grateful people are
very
kind uh the prison
directors love our group because the
fighting in the prison uh went down I'll
show you some cool pictures in tomorrow
maybe uh and that we had a very and some
of our
graduates from the prisons have very
nice businesses now like in Scottdale
uh
like one is a beauty salon and stuff
like that and uh it's going quite well
[Music]
okay uh he's talking about protecting
people from danger in Tibet it would
have been uh people carried away on a
stream by a river or something like that
I think in in the modern world I think
uh car accidents or things like that if
you see a car accident if nobody else is
stopping right sometimes the police get
irritated if you stop but if you're the
first person there you stop and you get
out and you help them I had a fun
experience in Ireland I I flew into the
airport in Shannon and I had to drive to
gallway and uh I rented a car it's a
challenge because they drive on the
wrong side of the road and uh sometimes
you forget uh but there was a car in
front of me and uh and in Ireland all
the fields were cleared by making walls
so there's stones in the fields they
didn't have any place to put them so
they made walls everywhere out of stones
so every road has stone walls next to it
and and I'm following this car and it
starts hitting the stone
wall and it finally it crashed and uh I
ran over there I stopped I ran over
there and it's four Catholic nuns in the
car I'm said you guys okay and they're
like we need to go to the hospital and
I'm like okay and I put them in my car
and and I thought it was so funny
because they don't know that a Buddhist
monk
is driving them to the hospital and but
uh if you're the first person stop and
help help people okay that's part of uh
giving that's a kind of G perfectionate
giving okay giving protection and that's
part of rat Nara once you commit to
Diamond way once you take your diamond
way
vows uh one of the greatest gifts is
protection okay uh or say helping people
who are in trouble okay
uh so there's a tradition uh in Buddhist
V uh the summer Retreat of the monks and
nuns and supposed to be two three months
in the
summer uh we will stay in Retreat mostly
uh and that one big reason is that
there's more insects in the summer and
uh you will kill them if you're walking
around uh so there's a
tradition of the monks and nuns to do a
summer Retreat and don't walk around
around on the grass a lot so he's
talking here
about actually protecting insects from
Hot and Cold or if you see some insects
drowning or like that he said look
what's the big thing you know you can
save a insect with one motion of your
hand you just you know reach in the
water and take them out of the water and
he said don't be
lazy and don't think their life is not
important their life's as important to
them as your life is important to you so
if you have a chance to save an insect
uh do it and he's not talking about you
have to sit at the side of the lake and
save bugs all day but if you see a bug
who's trying to get out you know just
reach in and help him out okay help him
get out help bugs when you can
especially roaches okay
all
right
okay Mina jimba see MBA is again he's
secretly referring to your secret vs
inside of Al he's secretly referring to
your secret vth because giving Freedom
From Fear is one of the four secret vows
of giving okay so he says here mimba
okay which means uh and by the way this
lrim is full of
Tantra uh and it's disguised as a
Elementary Book okay and it's kind of I
think it's
cool
uh when we talk about giving
protection from Fear it doesn't have to
be from a
distance l shik
but jind do you if you have a a bug on
your body who's enjoying your blood
that's also a kind of giving I have a
there's a teacher who you know who said
uh they like to feed the mosquitoes I
personally can't do it uh and by the way
it's dangerous in Arizona it's not uh
they have a special diseases and stuff
so you don't have to do that but but uh
anyway when you have a chance to save
any creature save it okay do something
okay don't be lazy you might be that bug
next time okay it's like remember that
okay here's a nice thing that mitry
taught me my other
grandchild you can buy this on
Amazon uh it's cheap and it's cheaply
made also and uh uh s and my TR nor
turned me on to it it's a it's a bug
catcher so we use jars we catch bugs in
jars and uh like
flies uh it's it's I've been catching
flies for I don't know 30 years and I
catch him and I take them outside and uh
then they said give this a try cuz the
jar is kind of it's a lot of
work and uh my record by the way is 20
flies in one day my record in one jar is
three uh but uh this is a a vacuum thing
and uh if you see a spider or you see a
fly it has a battery and you just turn
it on and it sucks the insect but it
doesn't hurt them it has a special net
and uh it'll suck the insect up and then
you take them outside and you just turn
it off and they they they fly away so I
think it's a wonderful thing and I
really like it uh it sounds like a
vacuum cleaner but and it's much faster
than a
jar and it's it's also works better
sometimes with a jar you kill the fly by
accident uh but this one works really
well and it's fun you feel like you're
on a
safari you know to get the wild Lion
Okay so I I recommend my tree turn
turned me on to
it yeah just a single motion with your
hand can save an insect then go for it
it's saving someone's life okay
uh when you're
doing when you're
doing and you are giving someone on your
breath you are giving them your
happiness uh that's also the Perfection
of giving so just doing
t uh in your imagination
is the Perfection of giving you don't
have to give a $100 or $1,000 you can
just give your breath on your breath and
that is the Perfection of giving
okay uh I like this picture of
meditation I I like to so I worked in
Manhattan for almost 20 years and um I
used to go up on top of a a building or
or something like that and meditate it's
very very sweet uh during your lunch
break and stuff like that you can go do
Tongan you can eat your sandwich and do
Tongan on top of some building somewhere
and uh it's a very beautiful practice
okay the best secret practice when
you're working in
Manhattan is the talking to the Buddha
from the bathroom
okay and I'll teach you my secret
meditation Mr bin is uh you go to the so
it's hard to get time to meditate when
you're working in a very busy office so
I was working in a crazy busy office and
there's no time to do tonr or you know
there's no time to to do your prayer six
times a day so I used to go to the
toilet and close the door
the stall and sit down on top of the
toilet
seat and I just sit there for five
minutes and I think everybody thought I
had some stomach problem or something
and I will do my tunduk I'll do my
prayers I just sit there and do my
prayers you know and it's kind of stinky
but it's okay and uh you can get privacy
no one's going to bother you and uh I
used to sit there and do my prayers and
then then one day I decided
um I will talk to my future
Buddha I said hey Mike you know and he's
like what and I'm like but by the way he
never
ansed uh but I'm like I know you can see
me right your future Buddha can see you
right Teresa future Buddha can watch
Teresa now in the bathroom sitting on
the toilet you know so I would talk to
him say hi hi you know I hope it didn't
take too long to become
Buddha and H if you have any advice for
me I'm open you know because Buddha can
see past present and future right so
supposed to be your future Vivian Buddha
can see you now and you can talk to her
and I think it's very healthy I mean you
might they might take you to the mental
hospital but uh you can talk to Vivian
Buddha and say you know how you doing
and am I getting closer and how's my
practice and and I think it's very
helpful okay I think it's a nice
practice okay so just don't talk too
loud in the in the
toilet
okay I used to use the office for a lot
of practice I got a lot of practice done
there
okay then he's going to quote bodh SAA
CH avatara which is entering the Deeds
of the bodh saas uh and we're studying
this famous famous book it was written
about 1,300 years ago it's the ultimate
book about bodis activity it's by Shanti
Deva Master Shanti Deva uh SII is
translating it and if you're interested
in Sanskrit we're studying the Sanskrit
also so if you you'd like to try to
learn Sanskrit I'm teaching Sanskrit uh
during the class so it's a shenzong
tower class okay so
Jim he's gonna quote
bhatara which is uh learning to act like
a bodis SAA and there's an interesting
discussion in Shanti dea's book and
here's the discussion okay k
[Music]
is giving a Perfection yes uh what's the
Sanskrit for
Perfection okay
sayam
param Americans say
param so it means gone and the English
word exit comes from it ex it so it
means to leave and pum means other side
of the ocean like to swim from San Diego
to Koto or something okay that's called
P all right then he says is giving a
part yes and by the way it's not Pam
it's
pam
iser pam iser
okay par
parizer the six Perfections are not
Perfections the six Perfections get you
to Perfection the the word Perfection is
a famous
mistake okay yeah it's not that your
giving is perfect it's that your giving
will make you perfect so we call them
PM but it's really part part of either
okay it it helpes you become perfect it
it's not Perfection it's not six
Perfections okay who is that Ding is
that me stop that uh so he says is
giving is
Donita is giving is the Perfection of
giving the Perfection of giving and we
say well yeah I mean Buddha taught the
Perfection of giving and then somebody
says it's not the Perfection of giving
and we say what why and they say there's
still poor people there's still poor
people you know did Buddha live on this
planet yes did did Buddha reach Buddha I
guess did Buddha do the six Perfections
yes did Buddha perfect Perfection number
one
yes did Buddha perfect giving yes so why
is there still poor people here and he
says then we have to talk about what
does it mean to perfect the giving it's
not that there's no more poor
people it's that the
willingness to give in the in the
Buddhist mind is perfect so the Buddha
has the Perfection of giving Perfection
of giving doesn't
mean that there's no more poor people it
doesn't mean that it means you are
willing to try you are always willing to
try okay why is there still poor people
if Buddha is perfect giver why is there
still poor
people that's come from their side yeah
that's coming from their side Buddha
cannot fix your seeds Buddha cannot give
you money seeds you have to give
yourself money seeds Okay Buddha's
giving is
perfect but you didn't
listen Okay his giving is perfect
but your seeds are your seeds I in fact
you want to hear something cool I can
not give you anything when Grandpa gives
you $100 who gave you
$100 you gave you $100 although must
have done I don't
know by the way he gave it I think he's
donating it to the family of the people
of the person who passed away uh this
week in in town but
uh yeah you got to understand what is
the Perfection of giving and you can be
perfect in your giving and there're
still poor people you cannot really
protect the
insect right if they have the
seeds you will you will protect them if
they don't have the seeds When You Reach
In The Water to save them you kill them
you drown them you see what I mean if
you've tried to save bugs from water
sometimes you end up killing them you
know and uh so the Perfection is not
that you protect their life the
Perfection is that you want to protect
their life okay uh but it's you got to
understand that about the in in
Buddhism when you're trying to help
people you are limited by their seeds
okay and and you have to get used to
that otherwise you will get uh
discouraged you will say oh I tried to
help three people and they got angry and
they told me to go to hell you know and
uh okay that's okay you're still giving
your Perfection is still perfect okay
you cannot control the results of your
practice you cannot when you're trying
to help other people you cannot control
what happens you cannot should you
try yeah should you do your best of
course will it always come out well no
we had a lot of problems here in diamond
mountain we just spent 20
years to offer people a place to do
Retreat you know that's all 20 years of
extremely hard work and um and some
people not happy some people have a bad
time and then you're like I I'm sorry
you know I'm just trying to give you a
place to get away from your phone you
know
I'm not trying to do anything wrong I'm
just trying to help you you know so you
can't control what happens which
means when you're in the bodh Safa
business you shouldn't get discouraged
okay like bodh Safa is a
hardheaded like Mr Ben you know that's
the head is very hard you know you try
to help somebody and they're not happy
and you say I'm sorry you're not happy
but I'll do the same thing again
tomorrow
you know I'll keep trying to make you
happy I I can't make you happy nobody
can make another person happy it's not
possible you cannot it depends on their
seeds but your
responsibility as a bodh Safa is to do
your best try to make them happy try and
and that means never get discouraged
okay you cannot
control what happens from
your good deeds you can't control don't
give up Mountain because somebody had a
bad time here it's not that that doesn't
make sense in Buddhism it doesn't make
sense you do your best to help somebody
and then if if if their seeds are
different they will have a terrible time
here and then you have to be patient
about that you don't make Bad Seeds
about your bad seeds you know like just
say I'm sorry you didn't enjoy D
Mountain we'll try to get you a swimming
pool next year you know and uh I'm sorry
you you didn't like the food or you know
I'm sorry you met a Ratt snake or you
know I'm sorry we'll try to ask them not
to Slither your way you know like that
you can't control everything a buddy
Safa has to have a sense of humor about
their practice you know did you up
today yes you know are you gonna go home
and quit no I'm gonna up tomorrow
also you know and that's bu he up okay
don't get so serious about everything
you can't control your the seeds that
people have okay and people will
criticize you you try to help them
giving away your money giving away your
time for years and years and then people
are like I I don't like the food so I'm
sorry you don't like the food you know
next time we'll we'll try to make better
donuts for you you know like that when
you're in the bodh of
business you can't listen to the
customer okay don't get freaked out okay
just keep helping them shut up and keep
helping okay bu offers have to shut up
and and keep helping okay and maybe
people will thank you and maybe they
will curse you but what else you going
to do you're going to quit you're going
to watch
Netflix you know I mean it's good I like
Netflix I like Korea soap operas but
uh but I get bored after like an hour
like that's all I can watch you know and
then you got to go back to being a buddy
sapper okay all right that's the best
business all
right uh
the you cannot measure Lord Buddha's
success by the econom e omic level of
the country you cannot that's not
connected that depends on the seeds of
the people who live in that country it's
not Lord Buddha you cannot judge Lord
Buddha you cannot judge the buddhis saas
by what's the economy right now that's
that's crazy they didn't create the
economy you created the economy they're
just trying to help you figure out how
to change it okay s
if if
the if the if the judge of uh the
success of Buddhist practice is that the
world
changes for other people who don't
practice then that's crazy you know uh
even non bodas practice giving so
means they don't they don't hold back
their giving who are not buddhis saus
Buddhists who are not buddhis saus are
still generous okay but you cannot judge
them uh by the E economy of the world
around them that depends on the people
who who are there in that world
okay I had a friend a Christian friend I
think I told you this story I was doing
a a three-week retreat in
Flaga I have have a I have a Christian
friend we grew up together since we were
in third grade we were eight years old
when we met each other we were both
around
60 and uh I invited him to come up and
and just hang out with me for a day or
two and he came up from uh Phoenix and
he came to Flag Staff and we had
interesting conversations he's a very
good Christian and I used to go to his
church for fun because they had better
Bible study in my church when I was a
kid when I was a little kid I sneak out
and go to Bible study at his church and
um and then he said uh we had long
conversations and he said it it kind of
disturbs
me you're you're bodh sappa thing and I
said why and he said well so in
theory a buy SAA could just collect good
seeds and live in a bubble will live in
a beautiful bubble you know their life
will be very happy very beautiful and
then all the people around them are
suffering you know and so in your
religion you know you say that buod saas
collect good seeds and then that bodis
saas is living in a Buddha
Paradise in
Flaga you know and then all the other
people F St for having you know snow and
stuff and he said 'I don't I don't like
the idea you know and I saidwell what's
what's your idea you know and then you
know you get into weird stuff
like there's
somebody making you suffer someone built
you someone created you and then someone
caused you to get cancer also and I'm
saying like is that a better bubble than
my
bubble like he's like hm
and uh so anyway I
think I think we are in a bubble and I
don't think you can get out of that
that's the way it is you can reach
outside your bubble you can give the
gift of the Dharma you can teach people
to plant better seeds but you cannot
control their bubble you see what I
mean say again yeah their bubble comes
from you yeah it does
leftover stinginess
yeah not wanting to share your bubbles
Pleasures
okay uh the Perfection of giving is a
mental practice it's not a physical
practice the the
willingness to give what you have is the
Perfection of giving
circumstances the seeds of the other
person may prevent them from receiving
your
generosity but your willingness to give
is the Perfection of giving okay in
other words it's not the success of the
gift it's the willingness to give is the
Perfection of giving you cannot predict
what you give all the thousand dollars
and he goes and buys nuclear parts and
blows up brainos sorties instead of
teaching it but I mean I don't know what
he's going to you know okay we don't
know you just have to do the best you
can and and be be generous and help
people you can't predict what they're
going to do with it okay it it doesn't
work like that okay
get
your Dona
means uh increase your willingness to
share and that's the Perfection of
giving you cannot control what the world
is doing you cannot control what people
do with what you give them you just have
to keep giving okay okay by the way give
wisely I mean there's a big thing about
Not Giving weapons to people not giving
drugs to people you know not giving
people things that will hurt
them uh and you have to do your best to
not hurt I
Know Rich parents who hurt their kids by
giving them too much and those kids
become useless and they can't do
anything and uh so I it's not the amount
that you give it's the wisdom use the
wisdom when you give
okay uh he says again he's talking to a
lot of monks and he says Chum means the
three parts of a Buddhist Monk's robe
the skirt the top and the second top and
he says uh if some poor person comes up
to you and says I need some cloth okay
then you have to be ready to give okay
the Readiness to give is is the
Perfection of giving okay should a monk
give their robes to another person and
they say no you should not okay I mean
I've done it if someone was really cold
and we were hiking someplace and I've
given them my shellter wear but in
generally generally you shouldn't give
away your robes okay uh but you should
be willing to give away you see the
difference are you willing to give me
your robes yes is it appropriate for me
to give you my robes no
okay means start
small uh give away easy things they
say give away vegetables in my case it's
not
difficult last night I was G away so
many
vegetables they always came back on the
plate I don't
know so uh they say start with small
things and and give just learn to give
people small things and then you can
build up from there okay CH means start
with small
things if you start with small
things in the end you'll be able to give
up your body if you have to okay start
with small things give away small things
all
day and in a while you'll be able to
give away your
body you can increase your generosity by
by giving things away from small things
start with small things constant Small
Things
uh next picture
I think it's a dead guy yeah here we
go my uh it's hard to find a picture of
a dead person online there's some kind
of
weird people don't like it people don't
want to put it on
them um we all have to
die we will all
die uh you can't keep
everything you have you will leave
everything I have this really nice
diamond ring in my
bag and uh I carried around last night
somebody's telling me about their
10-year-old I'm
like I should just give him the diamond
ring you know so I gave him the diamond
ring last night and I said you know and
then I started to regret
it you know and I was like maybe my wife
will be
upset but then I
thought you
know I'm going to leave it behind it if
I keep it I still can't keep it it's
still GNA be in the bag when I die so
Rob's gonna have to clean it out
probably Rob will get it
and you know someone's gonna get it I
might as well get the credit you know uh
I might as well give it away before I
die right so I don't know when I see
stuff like that still in my
bag you know I'm like well I might as
well give it to somebody who knows we
might get in a car crash on the way home
we don't know so might as well give it
to somebody before it's too late right
so R she wake up when you
die nor you can't take anything with you
might as well give it now okay you have
something nice give it to somebody get
some mileage out of it you know do
something nice before it's too late and
then then somebody else is going to give
it away for you right okay and and by
the way you
feel free when you give your stuff away
you know I don't have
anything you know I me all the good
stuff's gone except the bass guitar
band uh you know just give it give it
while you can you know have fun while
you you can because later what somebody
else by the way it's irritating for
other people to have to clean out your
stuff okay I don't know why gisha didn't
give this away now I have to clean it
out you know it's irritating for other
people trust
me if you get in the habit of traveling
light through life you're much happier
okay much much happier strip yourself
down to the things you really need you
know okay I got three shirts I got a
pair of shoes I got underwear to change
every day until I can get to a washing
machine you know like just drip it down
to what you really need and then give
the rest away feel you feel light you
feel happy
okay it'll be easy for you
to
give never be
satisfied with your giving keep giving
okay keep giving
okay uh if somebody asks you for
something uh give okay give keep giving
all
right now he has some uh advice is about
giving okay some uh what do you call
small print in the
contract okay young
J if you don't have anything to give
away and you're tempted to make some
money dishonestly he says forget it okay
just don't give anything away okay don't
think oh I'm a bodh sappa I have to make
more donation to The Latin America Tour
or you know maybe I can just cheat on my
taxes a little bit you know he says
that's not perfectionate giving
okay it doesn't count as generosity to
to get something dishonestly and then
give it away that's that's a wrong
approach better not to give anything so
again his
audience was both uh monks and lay
people and by the way he he got in
trouble in his time by teaching lay
people he he was criticized very you can
still read the books the people are dead
God knows where they are but he was
criticized heavily for teaching lay
people and and he says parin Dum Kim
the first three
Perfections are especially appropriate
for uh lay people who who are not monks
or nuns okay
why giving is easy right monks and nuns
are not supposed to have stuff what's
the second
one yeah ethics I guess lay people are
doing more business doing more family
stuff they they have more chances to be
ethical third
one
patience yeah there's a joke in Sage
techim Kim CH but
uh I don't know to not live a monastic
life takes a lot more patience okay
you're GNA be around more irritating
people I'm almost said
but okay you run into more irritating
people a little bit outside of a
monastery but there's plenty inside the
monastery okay uh
J uh this is a quotation from entering
the middle way which is chand's great
Classic on emptiness which I'll teach
you after we finish this after December
I think I
hope uh and he says uh chandi Master
chandik
says uh the first three Perfections are
are really especially good for late
people okay
okay there are certain gifts you
shouldn't make until you're at the right
level there's certain gifts you should
not make until you're at the right level
the gift gift of your body is one of
them okay uh to
to to give to give up your life to
another person to to lose your body to
another it doesn't mean you know body
parts that's fine okay as long as you
don't
die but to die for somebody else that's
we're not at that level we don't we're
not strong enough so don't give more
than you're able to okay don't give up
your body yet you still need it okay
there will come a day when you might it
might be okay but we're not there
yet every time the Llama says you're not
there yet people say I
am but you're not okay okay he
saysa it would be inappropriate to give
up your body at this point at this
level he says you are not allowed to
give up your body you have to take care
of your body right now you have to take
care of your body okay you have a
responsibility to take good care of your
body eat well exercise well take care of
your body okay it's not once
you once you're in the body St of
business your body is already other
people's body so you don't have the
right to hurt it you don't have the
right to overfeed it uh you don't have
the right to under exercise it okay that
body is not yours okay you already
dedicated it to other people you have a
moral responsibility to stay
healthy when the day comes that giving
up your body would be as easy as giving
up your
salads you can
he says then you can do it okay we're
not ready yet and by the way people who
try to do stuff like that they're just
showing off okay frankly they're just
showing off they they want people to
notice that they're willing to cut their
finger off or something Buddha said keep
your fingers you need them okay take
good care of your fingers okay don't
show off by doing some big bodies up a
thing that's just showing off okay
so we had a guy the nice thing about
having a grandpa teach you I got lots of
stories uh there were we studied millera
life in uh New Jersey when I was living
in the Mongolian
Temple and there was a young man uh we
studied Miller Rus life and milerapa
went off into the forest Medi this young
man uh he immediately
uh gave all his stuff away and moved
across the street into this little tiny
patch of forest and he said I'm GNA live
like mapia you know and as soon as there
was a cold day he was back
and it was so funny you know so forget
that kind of thing
okay I stayed in a cave once I was going
to meditate in a cave and at night there
were like a thousand spiders and I was
like I think I'll go to diamond mountain
and stay in one of those Retreat cabins
that has a
door
okay
okay uh he's gonna talk
about things that are not appropriate to
give away
okay Jim it's not appropriate for a monk
or a nun to give away their ropes
okay I mean unless someone were dying of
cold or something like that
um can I announce that other thing Jing
May tomorrow it's today or tomorrow
today ah what
time is it announc
victim okay I don't care 5:45 there will
be an ordination
here uh okay uh and you'll find out who
it
is when you come but if you're
interested to see a the ordination of a
novice Nan you're welcome to come okay
Janice is going to take ordination yeah
[Music]
[Applause]
I have an opinion which is uh you know
if people ask me to give them
ordination then here's my opinion uh I
think an ordained person should be
should stand out not from their
haircut and not from their clothes I
think they should be more moral than
other people they should have a higher
degree of
Integrity uh I mean in my
opinion uh you should be able to say
this person is a monk or this person is
a nun not because of their haircut and
not because of the clothes but because
they are more kind and they are more
ethical they refuse to be
unethical I I think you should be able
to identify a monk or Nun by the their
ethics and their behavior and and I
think even the robes and the haircut are
distracting I think they they're
uh I think in the modern
world in the old days it meant you're
not supposed to have sex with them
basically if you see a person with this
haircut and this clothes on you're not
supposed to have sex with him I
understand that uh but in the modern
world I think uh
it's distracting uh when uh a person is
wearing robes or their haircut is
different and I
think uh fewer people will talk to them
and I've seen that I've seen uh Western
monks and nuns and they just look weird
and and nobody wants to talk to them and
then they can't teach people and uh I
think um I strongly feel that if you're
asking me to ordain a person you know
you got to stick with my opinion if if
no if you don't want to then ask someone
else to ordain you traditional or
ordination get a haircut wear robes
nobody will talk to you your parents
won't talk to you
uh and uh I mean that's okay if you want
to do that that's okay if you want to
get ordained from
Grandpa then uh I'm not selling robes
and I'm not selling haircuts I'm selling
uh Behavior havior uh moral super moral
behavior and and I
think uh a Monker and nun should
be uh should Stand Out by their behavior
not by their appearance uh to me that's
real ordination
so that's the kind of ordination I'm
offering
okay
uh R Jima anyway it's inappropriate for
a ordained person to give away their
robes and I obviously if someone was
freezing to death you should give them
your robes in 10 seconds right that's
that's
fine Den he says it's inappropriate to
give certain gifts to monks and nuns for
example uh food
afternoon to to to try to make a gift of
food afternoon to a monk or none is
inappropriate they're supposed to take
those things okay and in this uh
tradition in the tradition I was brought
up in when you become a Monker and nun
you are given a choice whether to skip
your meals after
noon and I kept it for 15 years I didn't
eat after noon for 15 years uh and then
I started doing
yoga and I then I I needed to eat in the
in the afternoon you know because I I
was doing because of my yoga schedule I
had to eat uh and so I changed my eating
habits but um in this
tradition in the ancient tradition a
monk or nun should not eat afternoon
okay and in this tradition when you get
ordained you're given a choice and and
you can keep it for one day or you can
keep it for the rest of your life it's
up to you I generally
believe and and so nowadays I don't eat
until noon I I I don't eat uh afternoon
generally unless I have to have a
business breakfast at diamond mountain
or
something generally I don't eat before
noon and I think that's a good uh I
think it's healthy I think it's very
healthy for you and I think it helped me
in my business career that I didn't eat
until uh I didn't eat after 12:00 for
for my whole business career my
corporate career I didn't e after 12:00
and um I think it's very helpful I think
it's keeps your mind very
clear but it's up to you
okay
[Music]
okay he says uh monks nuns and non-
Buddhist monks and nuns Janes for
example uh they're not allowed to have
onion or garlic okay and uh he said
therefore it would
be inappropriate to offer onion or
garlic to a a Jane monk or like that
Jane
nun uh they say that uh there are
special animals that live in vegetables
that grow under the Earth so they don't
eat radishes they don't eat potatoes
they don't eat onion uh like that they
say uh you will kill small creatures if
you eat those
things
so to give something inappropriate to a
person from another religion that would
not be correct to give them you that's
not the Perfection of giving
okaya means stinky
foods and uh in a monastery or in a a
nunery you are
living packed close together with many
other people hundreds of other people
and you're debating every day three four
hours and it's inappropriate to eat
onions or garlic uh it's hard on
everybody so uh generally monks and nuns
don't eat stinky Foods
okay jimba uh offering a
scripture to someone whose intention is
to is to criticize it is is is not
appropriate okay give give a diamond
color Sutra to someone who intends
to uh just tear it apart or you know
that's inappropriate okay
CH du is a difficult expression here Chi
means to
die du means they want to
die and it could mean uh to help a
person who wants to harm another person
so it's
inappropriate uh to sell weapons it's
inappropriate to sell alcohol it's
inappropriate to give things to people
that will hurt them and then if by
extension if a person wanted to commit
suicide
you know you're you're not being a bad
bu sappa if you refuse to give them
poison okay or you refuse to give them a
weapon you know that's that's okay you
didn't break your buy up of us can you
buy me a gun I want to commit suicide
then you say no and they say but you're
a buy yes you have vows to give what
people ask yes so buy me a gun
no okay all right like that it doesn't
mean you have to give away everything if
it's going to hurt somebody don't give
it away
okay
um you are definitely not allowed to
share secret teachings with people who
are not ready or people who don't have
appropriate uh
initiation I I had two
nightmares this week
uh and I rarely rare I can't remember
ever having a
nightmare uh in the in many in my life I
can't
remember I have friends who have
nightmares every night they wake up with
the same nightmares somebody's chasing
them I never never have these nightmares
but I had nightmares this
week and uh I was like surprised and it
was
uh I was having nightmares about
people practicing Tantra inappropriately
you know not not following the the rules
for tundra or teaching people Tundra and
I had two terrible nightmares and uh so
I think we have to you know you have to
know the rules for sharing Diamond way
with people and uh so you know if you're
if you got secret teachings from
Grandpa uh Grandpa's policy is you have
to finish the 18 courses before you
start secret teachings I have tried many
exceptions they all failed I think all
of them okay so uh don't you know please
don't give people
teachings secret teachings uh until they
finish the 18 ACI courses okay that's
Grandpa's request and uh and then don't
make up stuff don't get stuff off the
internet there's the tantry cour is here
the 18 courses here are the best in the
world and they are the best in history
and they I think they're 20,000
Pages you can spend your whole life on
it you know you don't need to look on
the internet and get some weird thing
that's not anybody's lineage okay
there's you don't need it
if if you finish
the the 20,000 pages and you want more
let me
know
okay and I will check your homeworks
first and then I'll let you then I'll
give you some more weird stuff you know
but don't don't waste your time that
that uh Diamond way course is complete
and it's the most complete in history of
of Buddhism in this world and uh it's
pure and it's very clean and wonderful
and very
very lovely wonderful practice okay so
don't waste your time don't give me
nightmares okay uh they were terrible
nightmares of people getting lost in the
hell Realms and terrible you know so you
don't need that stuff
okay if if you get through the 20,000
pages and you you're still not satisfied
you know look me up and I'll give you
some more weirder
stuff but uh there's a lot of stuff
online it's it's not appropriate it's
not it's not Diamond way and
every uh what do you call it every
authentic Diamond way practice is in the
18 courses trust me okay
there's nothing more than that
okay and and it's it's a lifetime
practice you can practice your whole
lifetime you you will not get close to
the end okay so you don't have to do
weird stuff all
right don't give
me don't make me lose more hair
okay it's getting short short
supply okay uh no
means to teach the deeper teachings to
people who are not prepared who have not
finished their 18 courses okay that's
called num men num men means
inappropriate people to teach and I
tried you know I met people who I
thought they were special and it was a
disaster so be safe you know make sure
they finish the 18 courses if they're
not willing to finish the 18 Foundation
courses they not going to succeed in in
the diamond way you know if they say
it's too much work or you know then
they're not going to succeed in t anyway
so so don't do it okay all
[Music]
right so is it bodh activity to arrange
for the release of a criminal who might
hurt more people
no they should be tried according to the
laws of that country and locked
up yeah I'm not gonna say anything else
uh okay I mean it's not a kindness to
arrange for dangerous things okay it's
not a kindness it's being a bodh sappa
doesn't mean going and emptying out the
prison from people who might hurt people
I mean if if we can help them we can fix
them then okay go to the prison
teach dedicate your life to go teach it
to
prison and and do it for five six years
and then if there's people who you think
should be released then help them and we
have done that many
times uh but it doesn't mean we should
release everybody from the prison who
might hurt people
there are
certain objects in life that you should
not uh offer to people you know people
want to kill themselves or people want
drugs or things like that being a bhis
sappa doesn't mean you give everything
being a bodis sappa means you take
responsibility to give what's
appropriate okay without hesitation okay
we got a few more minutes hang in there
I know it's tiring to go for two class
like this uh but just hang in there I
swore when I was cooking in class in
India that I would make my students
suffer
worse and uh when the day came and I'm
following
through never give something without a
appreciation that that you will get more
back okay never give
anything part of a bodh saa's generosity
is the
awareness that they will get aund times
more back okay and it's not uh wrong to
think like that it's fine okay if I give
$1,000 I will get $100,000 and then I'll
give a $100,000 you see what I mean
that's fine that's fine okay all right
um
we got three minutes hanging
there this is uh talking about the
morality of giving and making hard
decisions okay as a bodh Safra you have
to make some hard decisions sometimes
you have so much money uh there's
many good things to give your money to
then as a b SAA the decision
of who you give your money to is very
much part of a bodh office way of life
we are
not giving your money you know I asked
my teacher there are many homeless
people in New York you know should I
help them out he said no you know he
said do your best make sure you're not
paying for someone's alcohol or drugs
and uh help them but but use your you
know do you want to help a children's
school or do you want to help uh a
homeless you know you have to make
decisions we don't have unlimited funds
we don't have give everybody
something but you do have to make
decisions as a bodh sappa where to put
your gifts where to put your giving and
that's part of being a bodh sappa okay
those hard
decisions about where to donate uh
that's a BH problem okay and you should
take those decisions with joy you know
and you should take them
decisively like the surgeon cutting when
they have to cut you know like you you
should be tough about your giving and
it's not wrong to say I'm donating to
your project and I want to see the
spreadsheets afterwards you know I want
to see the receipts you know I'm not
donating to some stupid that never
appears you know like that like it's
good to be
tough uh with your giving it's a kind of
responsibility okay I will donate to
your project but I want to see the
receipts I want to see the the tax
payments I want I want to make sure your
accounting is clean and if it's not
clean I want my money back and I'll give
it to somebody else okay so it's not
it's a part of a bodh saus giving is to
be responsible and to take
responsibility you know I I will donate
to your thing but I want to make sure
you're using the money right you know
and that's fine okay a body SAA is a
pain in the ask to take a donation from
because they want you to prove that you
used it well okay and that's should be
like that okay as a Buddhist sta you
should be tough uh when you give your
money okay and and you should
it's last
thing uh so we never had a we never had
a major theft from my company and we
were dealing with 300,000 diamonds a
day the tables were covered with
diamonds just open diamonds you know and
one handful is a million doar and we
just had tables covered with diamonds
you know and uh
and I used to have conversations with my
business partner and he and he said
listen Mike you know you have a good
heart you trust everybody uh but don't
make it easy for people to
steal you know because you'll hurt them
you know there's not everybody's so
Noble that they can just ignore a
handful of diamonds you know uh you have
to have
systems and you have to have cameras and
you have to have security doors and you
have to have armed
guards and uh that's part of a buddhis a
buddhis SAA has to respect other
people's property and a buddhis SAA has
to make sure it's not easy for people to
steal things because they will hurt
themselves you see what I mean a bodh
sappa has to make sure not to hurt other
people by making it easy to steal uh
bodh takes
responsibility to protect other people
from themselves okay and and so when
you're in the bodh a business I I
learned a lot on that day I and I kept
thinking about it I said I don't like to
mistrust people I would want I want to
put the diamonds on the table and he
said don't do it you know somebody's not
as strong as you they're going to steal
something and then you put them in
trouble you know so a bodh Safa has to
not make it easy for other people to
hurt themselves okay who might not have
that kind of control